There are some general rules to help us determine the running time of an algorithm, so we'll start
with a time complexity where that constant time complexity.
So any statement that does not depend on the input size in any way is considered a constant complexity
of what?
So.
If I told you to choose any random card from the card deck.
The first random number from here.
Any number?
They are not sorted.
So you you shuffle them and you choose the first one.
It's very easy.
You are choosing the first number and the first card.
So it's very easy to choose a random one and X is a specific element.
OK.
And access any specific random card without having searched through the entire cards.
In terms of coding, let's see that time complexity of one in coding such that system that are that
print alone.
Hello.
Or in the Java or print in C print F and Python.
We will use many coding languages through the course, so I will make a diversity.
And this system that our imprinting hello, we are not doing anything, just making a constant thing
at predicting message.
If we if we create and initialize a variable, also, we are not doing anything that depends on statement
or any input size.
Also, if we create a new K equals 15 times, said the plus 800, we are just making mathematical calculations
that are not depending on any input.
So the user and, well, not the user well, not able to enter anything.
Everything is clarified.
We have z equal to 15, so 15 times 15 plus 800.
It's very simple to calculate this would release or result in a time complexity, the total time equal
constant equal of one.
So this is the constant time complexity of what the next complexity time complexity is.
The linear time complexity of an linear running time algorithms.
What are widespread?
These algorithms imply that the program visits every element from the.
Linear time complexity of any means that the algorithms take proportionally longer to complete as the
input grows.
This is very important as the input the growth the algorithm will make take more time to be complete.
Let's take an example in the playing cards and then go to that coding.
Example, choose the ace of hearts.
Maybe if you shuffle the cards.
And the truth, pardon them, choose any, anyone, any of the cards.
Maybe.
If you are going to you are not at random, we are not going to choose a direct one.
The direct ace of Hearts.
So we need to make sure that it is ace of hearts and not anything else.
So we need to search or the deck for ace of hearts if we are lucky, we can.
Get the ace of Hearts at the first.
A card or we have 52 cards, we can get it at the last one or in the middle.
So this complexity time complexity depends on the number of the cards.
We start again.
We need to choose the ace of hearts.
So it is.
It is defined.
We need ace of hearts.
We not we don't need ace of spades or diamonds.
So.
We have 52, 52 deck in the deck, we have 52 cards.
We need to search through the cards.
Where is ace of Hearts, if we are lucky, we can found at the first card, but if our we are unlucky,
we can found it at the last.
Their card.
This depends on that number of the cards.
Imagine that we have 100 cards, so maybe we can find the ace of Hearts at the first pick card or the
card number 100, which the last card.
So this depends directly on the input.
So as we increase the number of cards, we increase the time complexity to find a specific card.
This is very important to understand.
So.
Encoding linear time complexity means that the algorithm our algorithms take proportionally longer to
complete as the input of growth.
For example, if we have a loop for inth, I would have equal to one and I less than or equal to an
eye plus plus and we need to print every time.
Hello?
We said that the system when we print a message or assign variables or doing anything not related to
that input, we consider it as a const.
OK.
So.
This loop will go go through from one to and it will be repeated and times.
OK, so.
If I enter and 10 time, then this printing hello will be printed 10 times.
If I enter any less like an equal to one million.
So this system that out the print and line will be executed one millionth time.
So here we depend on the N on the value of and so as that and as and value increase that execute that
the statements increases.
And this means that the algorithms take the proportionally longer to complete as the input grows.
So.
So printing one million message in during a time is greater than printing this message.
Like, ten times.
OK, so this is the linear complexity in terms of coding also and time complexity.
The total time for this loop is c times n c corresponds to the system that allowed the print the C.
Correspond to this line of code.
So as I told you, system that out that the brain is having a value see goes that constant time.
And here is from the loop, because the slope will be stopped at the end.
So the number of execution and the number of iterations throughout this loop is depending on the value
of.
And so and if I enter 10, it will be executed 10 times if I enter one million.
It will be executed one million times, so it depends on there and value.
OK, so this is seat times, and it was seen as and according to them, previous lessons that we have
seen that the higher value of N with we took it and we removed that constant that that is multiplied
by.
And so here in this equation, we have the the highest term to see an and and equal to one.
And so having power one and then multiplied constant with and is removed, we have therefore the oh
of and is the time complexity for this loop.
OK.
This.